Hi everybody and welcome back to
the channel. just a little quick
video here as I was searching
around for the high fat cream,
50% fat content cream here in Alberta and it's
really difficult to get hold of, it's incredibly
expensive and a quick Google search tells me
that everyone wants to add butter to lower
fat cream to make a higher fat cream......
that's not right so let's talk about why.
So if you've looked online about how to increase
the fat content of a cream, 99% of places will
tell you to add butter. Now whilst cream contains
butterfat, milk and cream products and butter
products, they are essentially combined milk fat
and water with some protein that's what they are,
so milk has any anywhere from 0.1 to 3.5% milk
fat (aka butterfat) and cream all the different
variations of cream that percentage number
is the amount of of milk fat aka butter fat,
it's the same thing ok, but when you make butter
you are adding a product that cannot re-emulsify
back into the initial product without the addition
of an emulsifier, it won't it it's a nonstable
emulsion at that point so you would have to add
something like a a natural emulsifier lecithin,
sunflower lecithin, egg yolks, you know that's
lecithin. Anything like that CMC gum guar gum
all those kind of things but they have lots of
other side effects and there's already enough
crap in the cream as it is, we don't need to
add any more products. So if you were to add the
butter put it in fridge after it's chilled down
it will separate then you've got to recombine it
but actually when you use it in ice cream butter
real butter gives you a disgusting mouth feel,
it gives you slimy textures on the spoon, on your
tongue, on your mouth, on your lips you have to be
really really careful with how much butter you
actually use so the proper way to do it is the
most simple way is to evaporate off the excess
water that's what's done at the first stage by
the dairies Under Pressure they remove water from
the initial product they take the raw milk and
that excess water is evaporated off to create
a higher fat percentage and at the different
stages they withdraw that product they want
to create, your 3% cream, 5% cream, 10% cream,
18 blah blah blah that's what they do. So here
we have 33% cream, so I'm doing some recipes
for a company back in London it's a startup there
it's a really exciting kind of thing we got some
great recipes we're working on together if you're
interested in that's something that you want to
do, you want to start an ice cream business, head
over to our website PolarIceCreamery.com and you
can employ our services to create all your random
custom recipes for your customers, to make sure
that they're as good as they can possibly be.
Anyway little plug over, I need 50% cream
double cream because that's what people
use over in England, I'm not going to go
out and spend $15 on 250 milliliters of of
high fat cream from a random Dairy here so
I simply took this and turned it into 50%
fat content cream and this is how I did it.
The first thing you're going to do is weigh out
the cream because there's an actual scientific
mathematical calculation that you need to do I
will put on the screen here the calculation I
did to achieve 50% fat content cream. So it turns
out I've only got 470g worth of cream here so to
get this to 50% this is the calculation needed I
need to reduce it down to 310g of total weight and
what that leaves us is a final cream with 50% fat
content 50% water content what you're going to do
is bring it up to a very low simmer and leave it
there you're going to need to stir this you're
going to need to agitate this please do not boil
your cream you will scold it you will change the
taste and the flavor profile and it will not be
pleasant this reduction took 45 minutes for me and
that was removing 160g of water from my 470g of
cream after that was done I check the weight here
in a bowl you can do this a couple of ways you can
weigh your pan with your cream in at the start as
a total weight once you've done your calculation
all you then have to do is pop the pan on your
scales to see where you're going or you can empty
it into a container and check either one works but
once it's all completely evaporated you're going
to empty your lovely high fat cream put it in a
container and put it in the fridge overnight to
completely chill down uh this has just come off
the hob it's gloriously thick it's not as thick
as you would think it this is exactly the same
consistency as UK double cream okay exactly the
same fat content it's been done and made in the
same way that the dairies make high fat cream
so you can use this in any recipe and it won't
give you that strange mouth feel and texture in
your mouth on your spoon in your on your tongue
on your lips this is the most economical way of
doing it just remove the water okay don't add
butter it really isn't the same thing so that's
it nice simple video here this is how to actually
make high fat cream this is how to make 50% fat
content UK double cream when you only have 33%
cream available this stands for any cream that
you have if you're in the US and you got your
36% I've been told that you can get 40 % heavy
whipping cream over there so that's some much
less water to evaporate off to increase increase
your fat content to 50% that's really really nice
you could technically do this with anything you
could do this with milk if you wanted to you could
put your high fat milk 3 and a half% full fat milk
in a pan and reduce it you need a lot of milk to
get your 50% cream but you could do it so there
you go a nice little scientific way of how to
correctly achieve high fat UK double cream if you
don't have it available this will work with any
cream that you've got whether it's pasteurized
Ultra pasturized doesn't make any difference,
remove the water, you'll be a happy bunny.
Anyway thanks very much for watching, don't
forget to like and subscribe and I'll see you next
time with my big fat 50% cream ice cream belly.